[Music]
if you randomly select a group of women
and ultrasound their uterus
the majority of them have fibroid tumors
by age 50.
and by most i mean
more than 80 percent of black women and
about nearly 70 percent of white women
half of white women already have
fibroids by their early 40s
and the same could be said for
african-american women in their mid-30s
after getting over the shock of how
widespread fibroids are
the next question becomes
why the racial disparity is it diet
stress environmental exposures
maybe whatever it is could offer a clue
as to what causes fibroids for example
african americans tend to have a lower
intake of fruits and vegetables
and fruits and vegetables appear
protective against fibroids particularly
citrus here in the black women's health
study though not apparently just citrus
juice
it's interesting if you measure the
levels of beta-carotene in fresh
surgical tissue samples of uterine
fibroids
and adjacent normal uterus tissue
obtained during hysterectomies
you find significantly lower
concentrations in the fibroids
in fact beta-carotene was not even
detectable in half the fibroid specimens
the same thing is actually found in
cancer most cancerous tissues tested had
undetectable levels of beta-carotene
compared to the normal tissue right next
to the tumor
so maybe decreased levels of
beta-carotene somehow plays a role in
causing these conditions
sounds like a bit of a stretch but you
don't know
until you put it to the test
but there have never been a randomized
controlled clinical trial of fruits and
vegetables for fibroids until
never
they did do a randomized controlled
trial of a kind of a fruit and vegetable
at the same time tomatoes
but for the prevention of fibroids in
japanese quail and most of my patients
are not
japanese nor
quail
the action of lycopene the red pigment
in tomatoes in
an animal model may not accurately
represent lycopene action in
humans
and indeed the harvard nurse's study
found no apparent link between lycopene
consumption and fibroids
so yeah fruits and at least green
vegetables may have a protective effect
but we won't know for sure until they're
properly put to the test
vitamin d is another possibility as to
why african americans disproportionately
suffer from fibroids women with darker
skin are more likely to be vitamin d
deficient as many as eighty percent of
black women may have inadequate levels
of vitamin d compared to only one in
five white women
vitamin d does inhibit fibroid cell
proliferation in a petri dish it may be
able to shrink tumors in your pet rat
but what about people
the population study did find that women
with sufficient vitamin d levels in
their blood had about a third lower odds
of fibroids consistent with the finding
that women who report lots of sun
exposure also appear to be protected
but until there's an interventional
trial where women are randomized to
vitamin d or placebo we won't know for
sure if vitamin d plays a role in
fibroid prevention or treatment or not
african american women are also
more likely to sprinkle baby powder on
their genitals
which may not only double the odds of
fibroids
but may increase the risk of ovarian
cancer the deadliest gynecological
cancer
internal memos show johnson and johnson
knew
about the cancer risk but still decided
to target african americans
think of us johnson johnson said as a
lifetime friend of the family a lifetime
cut short perhaps
by its baby powder or at least so said a
jury which recently awarded a family 110
million dollars in damages
on top of the 200 million in verdicts
from last year with thousands of
lawsuits pending
after internal memos revealed that
decades ago their own contracted
toxicologists were warning the company
that there are multiple studies showing
a cancer link and anyone who denies this
risk will be perceived by the public in
the same light as those who denied a
link between smoking cigarettes and
cancer denying the obvious
in the face of all evidence to the
contrary
[Music]
foreign